TUAN A. TRAN

+49 (176) 288-22670 ♦ Heilbronn, Baden-Württemberg, Germany

fanhtuan.tran2@bosch.com & LinkedIn profile & Github page

SUMMARY

I am an R&D engineer and technical lead with 10+ years of experience in software engineering and applied AI research (Natural Language Processing - NLP, Knowledge Graph, Autonomous Driving). I am currently seeking a full-time senior role in data science and machine learning in a company with big industry impact.

EDUCATION

Leibniz University Hannover

Hannover, Germany

Doctor of Natural Sciences (Dr.rer.nat) — Magna cum lauda

August 2018

• Topic: Natural Language Processing & Knowledge Graph

Saarland University, Max Planck Institute for Informatics

Saarbrücken, Germany

Master of Computer Science — Graduated with Distinction (Grade: 1.3)

May 2011

- International Max Planck Research School Master Fellowship
- Relevant Courses: Database, Artificial Intelligence, Software Engineering, Large-scale Graphs, Practical Security

Hanoi University of Science and Technology

Hanoi, Vietnam

Bachelor of Engineering — Graduated with Excellence (Grade: 8.9 / 10)

May 2008

- Excellent student research award
- Major: Computer Science (Minor: Information Systems)

High School for Gifted Students, Hanoi University of Science

 $Hanoi,\ Vietnam$

High school Diploma — Graduated with Excellence (Grade: 54 / 60)

May 2003

• Member of National Mathematics Olympiad team

WORK EXPERIENCE

Technical Lead

September 2020 - present

Robert Bosch GmbH — Global Services division

Stuttgart, Germany

- Lead engineering team to build a ML system that reduced processing time of customer requirements to 85% using hybrid models (NLP, Near-Duplicate Detection, rule-based classifiers).
- Work with DevOps team to streamline models from in-house GPU cluster to AWS EKS for 3 customers.
- Build backbone model using different data via Language Model fine-tuning techniques
- Support product owner and project leader in talk with stakeholders, help grow team (3 in 2019 to 11 in 2022).

Senior R&D Engineer

Jan 2020 - present

Robert Bosch GmbH — Mobility Solutions

Abstatt, Germany

- Developed Minimal Viable Products with autonomous driving team for internal use cases:
 - Brake Analysis: Processed 100 TB measure data to allow visualization in in-house dashboard (QlikSense).
 - Road Sign Recognition: Processed public and internal data (28 countries), developed retrieval and augmentation service for an in-house labelling tool that led to 13% model improvement.
- Contribute to publicly-funded project KI-Wissen (Work package 1.4 Knowledge extraction).
- Collaborate with corporate research: 4 internal reports, 1 patent application, 5 peer-reviewed publications.

Interim Sub-project Leader, Product Owner

Jan 2020 - August 2020

Robert Bosch GmbH — Mobility Solutions

Abstatt, Stuttgart, Germany

• Led an internal incubation project, defined roadmap with cross-functional teams, successfully integrated to a corporate top-level project, adding 3 more headcounts for the department.

Development Engineer

Sep 2017 - December 2019

Robert Bosch GmbH — Mobility Solutions

Abstatt, Germany

- Developed ETL to process internal video data; built semantic search functions (ElasticSearch, Stardog)
- Developed AI model to classify brake quality from test bench data with 80% accuracy using gradient boosting.

Research Intern

Jun 2016 - Sep 2016

IBM Research

Dublin, Ireland

• Extracted decision elements from meeting transcripts (project Debater)

Research Software Engineer

Aug 2011 - Aug 2017

L3S Research Center

Hannover, Germany

• Worked in 3 EU research projects (Qualimaster, ForgetIT, GLOCAL)

Freelancer Software Engineer

Backend Software Developer

Oct 2008 - Feb 2009

SaltLux

Seoul, Südkorea Apr 2008 - Oct 2008

Viet Intelligences

Hanoi, Vietnam

EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

2021 Member of Bosch Developer Advocate Network - DAN (gave internal tech talks & tutorials)

2020 Participated in nuScenes prediction challenge (top 4 finalists)

2016 Presented project results in CeBIT expo

2016 External reviewer WSDM 2016

2013 External reviewer RecSys 2013

SKILLS

Languages Python, Java, Go, Bash, SQL Platforms Linux, Hadoop, AWS, HPC

AI & Deep Learning Scikit, xgboost, Pytorch, HuggingFace, spaCy DevOps & MLOps Docker, Github Actions, MLFlow, Seldon, DVC

Automotive process V-Model (ASPICE), Functional safety standards (IEC 61508, ISO 26262)

Soft Skills Agile (Scrum, SAFe), leadership (SCARF, situational), project management

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS (since 2018 - See Google Scholar for publications during PhD)

- System and Method for Road Sign Ground Truth Construction with a Knowledge Graph and Machine Learning, US Patent App. 17/004,133. (See arXiv paper)
 Ji-Eun Kim, Cory Henson, Kevin Huang, Tuan Tran, Wan-Yi Lin.
- Feasible and Adaptive Multimodal Trajectory Prediction with Semantic Maneuver Fusion, IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) (link). Hendrik Berkemeyer, Riccardo Franceschini, **Tuan Tran**, Lin Che, Gordon Pipa.
- 2019 Using Knowledge Graphs to Search an Enterprise Data Lake, European Semantic Web Conference (ESWC) (link). Stefan Schmid, Cory Henson, Tuan Tran.
- 2018 A Trio Neural Model for Dynamic Entity Relatedness Ranking, The SIGNLL Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL) (link). Tu Ngoc Nguyen, Tuan Tran, Wolfgang Nejdl.

LANGUAGE PROFICIENCY

 $\ \, \text{Vietnamese}\,\,(native)$

English ($business\ fluent$)

 $German\ (good)$